Guide to the Priscilla Robertson Papers, 1889-2000
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Priscilla Robertson Papers
1889-2000
Robertson, Priscilla Smith
13.2 cubic feet (33 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Personal and professional materials related to author, professor, historian and former chairwoman of the Kentucky Civil Liberties Union, Priscilla Roberts (VC 1930), including correspondence, photographs, publications, diaries, teaching materials, and research materials.
Biographical Note
Priscilla Smith Robertson (1910-1989) was an author, professor, historian, and a former chairwoman of the Kentucky Civil Liberties Union. Born in Paris in 1910, Robertson was raised primarily in New England and attended Vassar College, graduating with her BA as part of the Class of 1930. Robertson served as editor of The Humanist magazine, and taught history at the Old Ballard School, Indiana University, Harvard University, Kentucky Southern College, and the Louisville School of Art in Anchorage.
Robertson's work includes The Revolutions of 1848: A Social History, published 1952, and An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th Century Europe, published in 1982. She did considerable work with the Southern poor in the 1930s, for which she was honored by the Southern Historical Institution in Lexington two weeks prior to her death. Robertson died on November 26, 1989.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains personal and professional materials related to author, professor, historian and former chairwoman of the Kentucky Civil Liberties Union, Priscilla Roberts (VC 1930), including correspondence, photographs, publications, diaries, teaching materials, and research materials.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Agee, James, 1909-1955; Broadus, Eliza; Guild, Aaron; Macneale, Anna; Macneale, Neil; Plimpton, George; Robertson, Ella Broadus, 1872-1945; Smith, Winifred; Kendall family; Macneale family; Plimpton family; Smith family
Organizations:
American Civil Liberties Union of Kentucky; American Civil Liberties Union
Subjects:
Civil rights--Kentucky; Sharecropping--Arkansas; Women authors; Women historians; Women periodical editors
Places:
Southern States--History--20th century
Document Types:
Diaries
Titles:
The Humanist
VCL Categories:
Education; Family; History and Historians
Encoding Information
Finding aid encoded by Jason Kovari, 19 Mar 2009. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, July 2025.
Series List
- Series I. Humanist Materials
  Includes mostly editorial correspondence.
- Series II. KCLU (American Civil Liberties Union of Kentucky) Materials
- Series III. Personal Correspondence
- Series IV. Diaries, 1890-1922
- Series V. Writings
- Series VI. Teaching Materials
- Series VII. Personal Materials
- Series VIII. Miscellaneous Materials
- Series IX. Biography
Container List
- SERIES I. Humanist Materials
  - Humanist Editorial Correspondence
    - A - F (Box 1)
    - Friedmann - Hook (Box 2)
    - Huber, 1956-1958 (Boxes 2-4)
    - I - J (Box 4)
    - Jones - LaBarre (Box 5)
    - Lamont - Lockwood (Box 6)
    - M - Overstreet (Box 7)
    - P - Wilson (Box 8)
    - Smith - Wechsler (Box 12)
    - Wescott - S (Box 13)
    - Sanders - Smith, W. A. (Box 14)
  - Humanist Miscellaneous Materials
    - Humanist Controversy and aftermath (Box 9)
    - Humanist: Old office materials (Boxes 10-12)
      Includes staff report, policy, and budget.
- SERIES II. KCLU (American Civil Liberties Union of Kentucky) Materials
  - KCLU Materials (Boxes 15-16)
  - KCLU Materials; Service boards (Box 17)
- SERIES III. Personal Correspondence, 1950-2000
  - A-B (Box 17)
  - Bendit-Brinton (Box 18)
  - Bruun-G (Box 19)
  - H-K (Box 20)
  - Kendall-Lockwood (Box 21)
  - Luscky-McKay (Box 22)
  - N-Plimpton (Box 23)
  - R-Taylor (Box 24)
  - Tatlock-Webber (Box 25)
  - Weismann-Wolcott (Box 25)
  - Postcards to Winifred Smith (Box 33)
  - Mother's letters to Winifred, 1889 (Boxes 32-33)
- SERIES IV. Diaries, 1890-1922
  - H.K.S. — Travel in Europe, 1903 (Boxes 32-33)
  - H.K.S. — Diary, 1910-1911 (Boxes 32-33)
  - A.M.S. diary, 1922 (Boxes 32-33)
  - Winifred Smith diary, 1890 (Boxes 32-33)
  - [Winifred Smith] diary, 1892 (Boxes 32-33)
- SERIES V. Writings
  - Books
    - Revolutions of 1848 - Letters (Box 26)
    - Revolutions of 1848 - Publishing (Box 26)
    - Revolutions of 1848 - Princeton Publishing (Box 26)
    - Revolutions of 1848 - Reviews (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Advertising (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Copy Editing (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Drennan, J. (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Italian Library (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Letters (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Literary Agent (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Pre-Publication Letters (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Readers' Report (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Rejections (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Rettig, C. (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Reviews (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Sources (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Statistics–Append. (Box 26)
    - An Experience of Women: Pattern and Change in 19th century Europe - Temple Publisher (Box 26)
    - History of Childhood - Bulletins (Box 26)
    - History of Childhood - Reviews (Box 26)
    - Lewis Farm (Box 26)
    - Buen (Box 26)
  - Articles
    - C.J. Reviews (Box 26)
    - Harper's (Box 26)
    - Harper's Commentary (Box 26)
    - Harper's Housekeeping (Box 26)
    - Harper's Letters to Editors (Box 26)
    - Harper's Publishing (Box 26)
    - Kentucky Constitution (Box 26)
    - My Great-Grandmothers Were Happy (Box 26)
    - Progressive Reviews (Box 26)
    - Published Articles (Box 26)
    - Sex (Box 26)
    - South Today (Box 26)
    - Student Barricades (Box 26)
    - Values (Box 26)
  - Unpublished
    - A.H.A. Talks (Box 26)
    - Fiction Stories (Box 26)
    - Priscilla Robertson Talks (Box 26)
    - Unpublished (General) (Box 26)
  - Sharecropper Materials
    - 1938 Student Group-Arkansas (Box 26)
    - Addresses and Letters (Box 26)
    - Agee, James (Box 26)
    - Arkansas Lawrences (Box 26)
    - Arkansas Sharecropper (Box 26)
    - Boyle (Box 26)
    - Butler (Box 26)
    - Florida Lawrences (Box 26)
    - Louise's Letters (Box 26)
    - Louise's Text (Box 26)
    - Memphis Convention (Box 26)
    - Missouri Highway (Box 26)
    - Mitchell (Box 26)
    - Mitchell's Film (Box 26)
    - Myrtle (Box 26)
    - Priscilla Robertson Work in Arkansas (Box 26)
    - Political Autobiography (Box 26)
    - Printed Sources (Box 26)
    - Publication – Temple (Box 26)
    - S.T.F.U. (Box 26)
    - Socialist and Communist Fight (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Publication Efforts (Box 26)
    - Ideas (Box 26)
    - Victorian Studies – Children (Box 26)
    - Sources for Children's Book (Box 26)
    - Notes for Children's Book: England, France, Germany, Italy (Boxes 29-30)
    - Notes for the History of Civilization (Boxes 29-30)
- SERIES VI. Teaching Materials
  - Indiana University
    - History 103, History 104, History 359 (Box 27)
    - Notes for Lectures (Box 27)
    - Herodotus and Greece Notes (Box 27)
    - Student Comments (Box 27)
    - Final Exams (Box 27)
  - KSC (Kentucky Southern College)
    - Tests (Box 27)
    - Letters to art school students (Box 27)
    - Student records (Box 27)
    - Modern Europe (Box 27)
- SERIES VII. Personal Materials
  - Priscilla Robertson Personal Materials (Box 31)
    Includes: photographs, Academy Award, college, public service, passports, childhood expression, travel, dreams, letters.
- SERIES VIII. Miscellaneous Materials
  - Arts, letters, and social science (Box 28)
  - Poetry (Box 28)
  - Society (Un-American activities, population, religion, peace, the South) (Box 28)
  - Art (photography, costumes) (Box 28)
  - Language (handwriting, literature, words) (Box 28)
  - Recreation (puzzles, solitaire…) (Box 29)
  - Education (progressive education, Vassar, international conference, Ballard philosophy) (Box 29)
  - Theater (programs) (Box 29)
- SERIES IX. Biography
  - General
    - Addresses (Boxes 32-33)
  - Smith Family
    - P.S. (Priscilla Smith?) - letters, articles, book reviews, photos (Boxes 32-33)
    - H.P.S. - photos, heresy trials, letters, writing (Boxes 32-33)
    - Winifred Smith - photos, teaching, autobiography, letters, writing (Boxes 32-33)
    - Smith ancestors - photos, printed materials (Boxes 32-33)
  - Macneale Family
    - Anna Macneale (Boxes 32-33)
    - Genealogy (Boxes 32-33)
    - Autobiography—Neil Macneale (Boxes 32-33)
  - Kendall Family
    - J.P.K. (J. P. Kendall) (Boxes 32-33)
    - I.P.K. (I. P. Kendall) (Boxes 32-33)
    - H.P.K. (H. P. Kendall) (Boxes 32-33)
    - Kendall ancestors (Boxes 32-33)
    - E.W.K. (E. W. Kendall) (Boxes 32-33)
  - Plimpton Family
    - George A. Plimpton (Boxes 32-33)
    - E. Plimpton (Boxes 32-33)
    - Plimpton genealogy (Boxes 32-33)
    - Aaron Guild (Boxes 32-33)
    - Plimpton photographs (Boxes 32-33)
  - Miscellaneous ancestors
    - Humphrey (Boxes 32-33)
    - H.K.S. (Boxes 32-33)
    - E.R.E. (Boxes 32-33)
    - Ella B. Robertson (Boxes 32-33)
    - E.B.R. (Ella B. Robertson) writings (Boxes 32-33)
    - Robertson ancestors (Boxes 32-33)
    - Robertson ancestors - photos (Boxes 32-33)
    - Cary's siblings (Boxes 32-33)
    - Miss Lottie letters (Boxes 32-33)
    - A.T.R. Jr. (Boxes 32-33)
    - Easley letters (Boxes 32-33)
    - Eliza Broadus (Boxes 32-33)